<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Max Johnson</title>
    <link href="https://maxj.phd/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://maxj.phd"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://maxj.phd/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>1-Parameter Deformations of Stable Categories (WIP)</title>
        <published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://maxj.phd/posts/defos/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://maxj.phd/posts/defos/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction-and-references&quot;&gt;Introduction and References&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explore the emerging study of so-called deformations of stable $\infty$-categories. There are a number of perspectives from which to view these deformations, each providing its own insight into the overall narrative. As such, this post will draw from a number of sources:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burklund-Hahn-Senger, Galois Reconstruction&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moulinos, Geometry of Filtrations&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gheorghe-Isaksen-Krause-Ricka, $\mathbb{C}$-motivic modular forms&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2111.15212&quot;&gt;Gregoric&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, Moduli Stack of Oriented formal groups and cellular motivic spectra over $\mathbb{C}$.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1803.01804&quot;&gt;Pstragowski&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, Synthetic Spectra and the Cellular Motivic Category&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our exposition will begin with an axiomatic approach to 1-parameter deformations before proceedings to discuss various machines for constructing them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: This story has been developed by many authors over many papers. This blog post does not do the full narrative justice, and does not include all of the papers and results that have led to the ones it does include. In distilling the concept into this post, I have necessarily omitted work and authors that ought to be included, for which I apologize.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-parameter-deformations-an-axiomatic-approach&quot;&gt;1-Parameter Deformations: An Axiomatic Approach&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We begin with Burklund-Hahn-Senger&#x27;s axiomatic approach to 1-parameter deformations. Rather than simply present their definition immediatley, however, I would like to first explain what the goal is. Let $C$ be a stable $\infty$-category. A (1-parameter) deformation of $C$ ought to roughly consist of a second stable $\infty$-category $C_{def}$ living over $C$ via a realization functor
$$
Re: C_{def}\to C
$$
which is usually expected to be highly structured. The primary idea will be to lift questions about $C$ to the larger category $C_{def}$, study them therein and then answer the original question by applying $Re$. As such, the more structured $Re$, the more effective this method can be.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, let us impose some further assumptions that are satisfied in most (all?) cases of interest. First, let both $C$ and $C_{def}$ be presentably symmetric monoidal stable $\infty$-categories. This means, among other things, that they both have symmetric monoidal tensor products preserving colimits in each variable. As a result, both categories will be self-enriched with mapping objects given by the right adjoints of tensoring with a fixed object. It is then natural to ask that $Re$ not only be symmetric monoidal but also a left adjoint so that all functors and categories live in $Pr^L$, the category of presentable $\infty$-categories and left adjoints between them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some early applications, which existed before the formalism became apparent, this was already enough. However, if our goal is to lift questions from $C$ to $C_{def}$ systematically, we ought to have some sections of $Re$ that allow us to do so while preserving structure. The first we will ask for is easy to motivate: the category $C_{def}$ ought to be not only self-enriched, but also enriched over $C$ compatibly. One way to formalize this is to ask for $C_{def}$ to be an algebra over $C$. Explicitly we ask that there be a symmetric monoidal left adjoint&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
c: C\to C_{def}
$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;providing our first section of $Re$. This is commonly referred to a tensoring of $C_{def}$ over $C$, and provides the desired enrichment. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axiomatically this will be the only section we demand; however, in practice it will be fruitful to have several. Perhaps counterintuiviely we will want to ask the other sections to be less structured. For example when $C=Sp$ is the category of spectra, the assumptions on $c$ are already enough to specify it unqiuely given $C_{def}$, as everything is determined by where there spheres $\mathbb{S}[n]$ go as these generated under (filtered) colimits. But then these too are determined by the image of $\mathbb{S}$ as $c$ will preserve suspensions. Lastly, $\mathbb{S}$ itself is the monoidal unit, and so must be sent to the monoidal unit of $C_{def}$. We will return to the question of sections of realization when we address specific examples later on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have so far discussed seems a reasonable notion of deformation; however, we are specifically interested in 1-parameter deformations. This extra specification comes in the form of a certain &amp;quot;basis&amp;quot; for $C_{def}$. Write $1_C$ for the monoidal unit of $C$. Its (de)suspensions $1_C[n]$ we will think of as the first &amp;quot;axis&amp;quot;. The functor $c$ acts by $c(1_C[n])=1_{C_{def}}[n]$ by the same arguments as we applied to the case $C=Sp$ above. The new &amp;quot;direction&amp;quot; in this second deformation will consist of a choice of homomorphism:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
i:\mathbb{Z} \to \ker\left(\pi_0Pic(C_{def})\to \pi_0Pic(C)\right)
$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the above is potentially intimidating notation for a simple concept: we would like to pick a second &amp;quot;axis&amp;quot; of objects $i(n)$ such that $i(0)=1_{C_{def}}$ but $Re(i(n))=1_C$ for all $n$. In effect, we are selecting a second collection of &amp;quot;shifts&amp;quot; of the unit which die under realization. Finally we need to ask that these two axes be &amp;quot;enough&amp;quot; to generated $C_{def}$ over $C$. To formalize this, we first ask that $C$ have a collection of compact, dualizable generators $K_\alpha,\alpha\in I$ and we insist that $C_{def}$ be generated by the objects $K_\alpha\otimes i(n)$ as both indicies range. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often the case that the original shifts of the unit $1_C[n]$ are among the $K_{\alpha}$. We will denote by $C^{cell}$ the objects generated by these shifts of the unit and $C_{def}^{cell}$ the objects generated by the $1_{C_{def}}[n]\otimes i(m)$. We will unify notation and denote the shifts of the unit in $C$ as simply $1[n]$ and define $1[n,m]=c(1[n])\otimes i(m)$. With this convention, $Re(1[n,m])=1[n]$. We define $X[n,m]=X\otimes 1[n,m]$ for any $X\in C_{def}$.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will call such a pair $(C,C_{def})$ a deformation pair. A careful reader will note that we have omitted an axiom from the BHS paper. For our purposes, this is best thought of as a specialization. We say that a deformation pair is of filtered type if in addition it satisifies&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
Map(i(a),i(b))\to Map(1,1) \text{ induced by } Re \text{ is an equivalence whenever } a\lt b
$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A main theorem of BHS Appendix C is that all filtered type deformation pairs may be realized using a concrete construction involving filtered objects in $C$. Before we turn out attention to such objects, let us first review some of the original deformations of interest to homotopy theorists.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;cellular-mathbb-a-1-homotopy-over-mathbb-c&quot;&gt;Cellular $\mathbb{A}^1$-homotopy over $\mathbb{C}$.&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let $SH(k)$ denote Voevodsky&#x27;s stable $\infty$-category of $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motives over a field $k$. This category is naturally bigraded as there are two natural families one might consider to be spheres. First, $SH(k)$ is stable so that there is a family of spheres given by the formal suspensions of the unit $1[n,0]=1[n]$ where the left hand side is the canonical suspension in a stable $\infty$-category. The second grading arises from considering the object $\mathbb{A}^1-0=\mathbb{G}_m$ to be a circle in its own right. Conventionally we put $1[a,b]=1[a-b]\otimes \mathbb{G}_m^{\otimes b}$. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When $k=\mathbb{C}$, the analytic topology on schemes provides a realization functor $Re:SH(k)\to Sp$ to spectra. It turns out that $Re(\mathbb{G}_m)=\mathbb{S}[1]$, so that our indexing convention is a natural one in view of the above sections. We will assume we are working over $k=\mathbb{C}$ to make use of this functor. It is worth noting that subfields of $\mathbb{C}$ also recieve such a realization functor combined with an induced Galois action, which is the primary focus of the Burklund-Hahn-Senger paper.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fix a prime $p$, and let us implicitly $p$-compelete all objects. Further, let us restrict to the category of cellular objects $SH(\mathbb{C})^{cell}$. This contains all objects of &amp;quot;topological origin&amp;quot; but also many algebrogeometric objects of interest. For example, the motivic spectrum representing motivic cohomology $H\mathbb{Z}$ is cellular. By choosing compatible systems of primitive $p^n$th roots of unity, we may construct maps $\tau_n: 1[1,0]\to 1[1,1]&#x2F;p^n=\mathbb{G}_m&#x2F;p^n$ which in the limit give a map on $p$-complete objects $\tau:1[1,0]\to 1[1,1]$. It is customary to adjust this so that $\tau$ is map $1[0,-1]\to 1$. Because the domain is the monoidal unit, the map $\tau$ extends to a self-map of all motivic spectra via tensoring. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple construction controls a shocking amount of structure in the cellular category. The first important realization (pun intended) is that the collection of objects on which $\tau$ acts invertibly is equivalent to the category of $p$-complete spectra. This was originally shown by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;0901.1632.pdf&quot;&gt;Duggar-Isaksen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; via a computational argument: they identify the bigraded homotopy groups $\pi_{a,b}(-)=\pi_0Map(1[a,b],-)$ of the $\tau$-inverted unit with thoses of the sphere which, essentially because $Re$ preserves colimits, forces it to be fully faithful on $\tau$-inverted objects. For essential surjectivity one shows that $Re$ has a suitable section.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This result ought to be considered the identification of a &amp;quot;generic fiber&amp;quot;, i.e., the result of setting $\tau=x$ for $x\in \mathbb{A}^1-0$. What remains is to make sense of the special fiber $\tau=0$. Of course, this is not imeddiatley defined in our categorical setting, we need to first define what killing $\tau$ means internal to the motivic category before we can try to describe it externally. Fortunatley, something of a miracle occurs. Recall that the unit of a symmetric monoidal stable $\infty$-category is tautologically an $E_\infty$-ring. What we would ideally be able to ask for is that $SH(k)&#x2F;\tau$ be defined by killing $\tau$ in the unit and taking modules. Famously, the naive cofiber of a map of commutative ring objects need not admit a multiplicative structure. However, by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1701.04877&quot;&gt;Gheorghe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, this happens to be the case for $\tau$, i.e. the map $1\to 1&#x2F;\tau$ is on of $E_\infty$-rings. As such, we may define:
$$
SH(k)&#x2F;\tau := Mod(SH(k), 1&#x2F;\tau)
$$
and we may attempt to identify this category. A first hint at what it ought to be was provided by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maxj.phd&#x2F;posts&#x2F;defos&#x2F;TODO&quot;&gt;Isaksen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maxj.phd&#x2F;posts&#x2F;defos&#x2F;TODO&quot;&gt;Isaksen-Xu&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which identify $End(1&#x2F;\tau)$ with $Ext_{BP_*BP}(BP_*,BP_*)$, the $E_2$-page of the Adams-Novikov spectral sequence for the sphere. Another interpretation of this $Ext$ is as the endormophisms of the unit in a derived category of $BP_*BP$-comodules. Indeed, in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1809.09290&quot;&gt;GWX&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; it is shown that this upgrades to a full categorical statement, a bounded subcategory of $SH(k)^{cell}&#x2F;\tau$ is equivalent to an &amp;quot;even&amp;quot; subcategory of the bounded derived category of comodules. It has since been shown by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1803.01804&quot;&gt;Pstrągowski&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that this can be improved to an identification of all cellular $1&#x2F;\tau$-modules with the even subcategory of Hovey&#x27;s category of stable comodules over $BP_*BP$, which differs slightly from the derived category but is for technical reasons more pleasant to work in. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final piece of this puzzle strengthens the relationship to the Adams-Novikov spectral sequence. The map $\tau$ has a Bockstein spectral sequence of the form:
$$
\pi_{*,*}1&#x2F;\tau [\tau] = Ext_{BP_*BP}(BP_*,BP_*)[\tau] \Rightarrow \pi_{*,*}1
$$
and it encodes data identical to the Adams-Novikov. In effect, there is a differential $d_{2r}(x)=\tau^{r-1}y$ in the Bockstein exactly when there is a differential $d_{2r}(x)=y$ in the Adams-Novikov (recall that the odd differentials are trivial for degree reasons).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, we may view the category $SH(k)^{cell}$ as a deformation of spectra along the Adams-Novikov Spectral sequence. Indeed, it ends up satisfying the axioms of a deformation pair above. Even stronger, it is of filtered type and provides the first example of the filtered-module deformations we wish to study in general. This claim is of course a bit ahistorical, as the general theory was motivated by this example. The original filtered model is due to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1810.11050&quot;&gt;Gheorghe-Isaksen-Krause-Ricka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, we now turn our attention to it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation is rather simple. The deformation perspective hints that building $SH(k)^{cell}$ should involve two ingredients: spectra and teh Adams-Novikov Spectral Sequence. Their theorem is that this can be made formal. Let us first recall the notion of filtered objects and some related ideas.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;filtered-objects-tower-functors-and-their-deformations&quot;&gt;Filtered Objects, Tower Functors, and Their Deformations&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First some notation. Let $C$ be any $\infty$-category. Denote by $\mathbb{Z}_{\geq}$ the poset category with a morphism $n\to m$ if and only if $n \geq m$. The category of filtered objects in $C$, denoted $C^{fil}$, is the functor category $Fun(\mathbb{Z}_{\geq}, C)$. Let the undecorated $\mathbb{Z}$ denote the discrete category of integers with only identity morphisms. Then the category of graded objects in $C$, denoted $C^{gr}$, is the functor category $Fun(\mathbb{Z}, C)$.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let $X(\bullet)$ be a filtered object. We write $X(-\infty)$ for the colimit $X$ considered as a diagram in $C$ and likewise $X(\infty)$ for its limit. It is standard to refer to $X(-\infty)$ as the underlying object of $X$. For reasons of foreshadowing, we will refer to it instead as the realization and denote $X\mapsto X(-\infty)$ by $Re(X)$. A filtered object may be visualized as a sequence
$$
X(\infty)\to ... \to X(n+1) \xrightarrow{x_{n+1}} X(n) \xrightarrow{x_n} X(n-1) \to ... \to X(-\infty).
$$
To every filtered object we associate a graded one known as its associated graded. We denote this functor by $gr(X)$ and it is defined by the formula:
$$
gr_q(X)=cofib(x_q)
$$
Perhaps one of the most important themes in algebraic topology and stable homotopy theory is the fact that to such a filtered object we may associate spectral sequences. If $H_*$ is a suitable functor, applying it to the associated graded gives a spectral sequence (ignoring issues of convergence) of the form:
$$
H_*(gr_*X) \Rightarrow H_*(Re(X))
$$
A more recently understood structure is that the process of &amp;quot;flipping pages&amp;quot; in the spectral sequence may be realized as an endofunctor of filtered objects, i.e. under suitable assumptions on $C$ and $H$ which are satisfied in our cases of interest, there is a lax (symmetric) monoidal functor:
$$
Dec: C^{fil}\to C^{fil}
$$
such that the $E_1$ page of $Dec(X)$ is the $E_2$ page of $X$ up to regrading (c.f. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.mn.uio.no&#x2F;math&#x2F;personer&#x2F;vit&#x2F;rognes&#x2F;theses&#x2F;hedenlund-thesis.pdf&quot;&gt;Hedenlund&#x27;s Thesis&#x27;s Part 2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may then think of the promised GIKR result as follows. There is a lax symmetric monoidal functor $Ad_{MU}:Sp\to Sp^{fil}$ such that the spectral sequence associated to $Ad_{MU}(X)$ is the Adams-Novikov for $X$. As a result, the object $Ad_{MU}(\mathbb{S})$ is an $E_\infty$-ring and so too is $Dec(Ad_{MU}(\mathbb{S}))$. As such we may consider its category of modules $Mod(Dec(Ad_{MU}(\mathbb{S})))$. The GIKR theorem is that $SH(k)^{cell}$ is equivalent to an even variant of this module category.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This result essentially suggests its own generalization to other spectral sequences. Namely, given the input of a lax monoidal functor $T:C\to C^{fil}$ we can construct a deformation of $C$ by taking the category of modules over the image of the unit $Mod(T(1))$. When $Re(T(1))=1$ it can be shown that this data forms a 1-parameter filtered deformation of $C$ whose bigrading comes from the fact that a filtered object has two natural shift functors, one levelwise and one that reindexes. For a filtered object $X(\bullet)$ let $X(\bullet)[1,0]$ denote the levelwise suspension (which is also the formal suspension in the stable $\infty$-category of filtered objects) and let $X(\bullet)[0,1]$ by the shift 
$$
X[0,1](n) = X(n-1) 
$$
Indeed BHS do not only that this yields a deformation, but also show that given any other filtered type 1-parameter deformation $(C_{def},C)$ there is a functor $i_*:C_{def}\to C^{fil}$ such that $C_{def}\simeq Mod(i_*1)$. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this setting, as hinted earlier, the functor $T$ satisfies (potentially up to a localization) our desire for a more interesting section of $Re$.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thread-structures&quot;&gt;Thread Structures&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viewing $1[a,0]$ and $1[0,b]$ as two axes of a deformation, a threading structure is a natural transformation of the form $\tau:1[0,-1]\to 1$ stitching them together. Again the notational overlap is intentional as this threading will play the same role as the motivic $\tau$. In $C^{fil}$ the threading is quite easy to define. The internal maps $x_q$ within a filtered object $X(\bullet)$ compile to a (tautologically commuting) map of filtered objects $X[0,-1]\to X$. This map lifts to any category of modules in filtered objects via tensoring-up. Note now that we can already compute the outcome of the special and generic fiber. Taking the cofiber of $\tau$ will yield the associated graded and inverting $\tau$ is equivalent to realization. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result we recover the structural results of the motivic setting using the GIKR topological reconstruction; indeed, we can do it without completing at a prime first. In fact this allows us to lift this special-generic fiber philosophy to all of our filtered module deformations: we will have cofibers of $\tau$ encoding $E_1$ pages of spectral sequence (the difference in indexing arises from Decalage) and we will have $\tau$-invertible objects recovering (localization of) the original categories. Moreover, a careful inspection of how one builds a spectral sequence from a filtered object reveals that again the $\tau$-Bockstein will encode the original spectral sequences up to a formally adjoined element.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;some-other-examples&quot;&gt;Some other examples&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should note that there are a few more models of this philosophy not fully captured by our discussion. The Adams Spectral Sequence itself has at least two. Over spectra, the original categorification of the Adams Spectral Sequence of an Adams-Type ring spectrum $E$ is the category $Syn_E$ of E-synthetic spectra developed first in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1803.01804&quot;&gt;Pstrągowski&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This category has a number of formal properties making it preferable to working with the analog in the filtered setting, and is also larger containing objects that are not cellular. Moreover, it is in this category that we get a true indenfication of the special fiber with (a subcategory of) Hovery&#x27;s category of stable comodules.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is likely that the synthetic spectra machinery could be generalized beyond spectra (admittedly I have thought about this on and off for awhile), more recent work of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2110.03669&quot;&gt;Patchkoria-Pstrągowski&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; provides an extremely general setting for studying categorifications of Adams spectral sequences and exhibits many of the nice properties both of synthetic spectra and the overall deformation story above.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most substantially different model I would like to mention was developed by Rok Gregoric by first considering nonconnective versions of Lurie&#x27;s spectral algebraic geometry and then, motivated by connections between the classical moduli stack of formal group laws and the category of spectra, constructing a spectral algebraic moduli stack of oriented formal groups $M$. He first proves that the category of spectra is equivalent to an ad-hoc notion of Ind-coherent sheaves on $M$ and then shows that by taking a connective cover (affine-locally) $\tau_{\geq 0}M$ taking ind-coherent sheaves recovers $SH(k)^{cell}$. He then shows that the classical moduli stack of formal groups $M^{\heartsuit}$, which is equivalent to a variant of derived $MU_*MU$-comodules, maps to $\tau_{\geq 0}M$ as a closed immersion with invertible ideal sheaf, which he calls an extended Cartier Divisor. Its completment is then the connective cover map $M\to \tau_{\geq 0}M$, providing a stacky perspective on the special&#x2F;generic fiber philosophy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;geometry-of-filtrations&quot;&gt;Geometry of Filtrations&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to end this post on the machinery of deformations by providing a more algebro-geometric perspective on filtered objects. Namely, in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;1907.13562.pdf&quot;&gt;Moulinos&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; it is shown that the category of filtered spectra is equivalent to the category of quasicoherent sheaves on the spectral stack $\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m$ extending a result of Simpson on filtered vector spaces and the classical version of the same stack. Let us define these notions more carefully before proceeding.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, write $\mathbb{S}[X]$ for the suspension spectrum of a space $X$. We will write $\mathbb{A}^1$ for the affine spectral scheme $Spec \mathbb{S}[\mathbb{N}]$. Not that $\pi_{*}\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{N}]=(\pi_{*}\mathbb{S})[t]$. Then $\mathbb{G}_m$ is defined similarly to be $Spec\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{Z}]$. The inclusion $\mathbb{N}\to \mathbb{Z}$ induces $\mathbb{G}_m\to \mathbb{A}^1$ which we think of as analgous to the usual inclusion of the group of units in classical algebraic geometry. Moreover, the &amp;quot;diagonal&amp;quot; $\mathbb{N}\to \mathbb{N}\times \mathbb{Z}$ induces a $\mathbb{G}_m$-action on $\mathbb{A}^1$ and we take its homotopy orbits (taken in fpqc spectral sheaves) to produce the stack $\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m$. This stack is geometric with atlas provided by the quotient map $\mathbb{A}^1\to \mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m$. There is one more player in this story so-far unmentioned, which is the classifying stack $B\mathbb{G}_m$.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proof of his main theorem begins by identifying graded spectra with the category $coMod(\mathbb{S}[\mathbb[Z]])$ of comodules over the bialgebra $\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{Z}]$. To understand this, first we let $\pi:\mathbb{Z}\to pt$ be the unique map to a point and write $\pi^*$ for the induced functor $Sp^{gr}=Fun(\mathbb{Z}, Sp) \to Fun(pt,Sp)=Sp$ which is given by taking constant presheaves. This admits a left adjoint $\pi_!$ which concretely on a graded object acts by summing together the pieces. The lemma then follows from noting that the functor $\pi_!:Sp^{gr}\to Sp$ fits into a comonadic adjunction
$$
\pi^*: Sp \leftrightarrows Sp^{gr}:\pi_{!}
$$
identifying the right hand side with the category of coalgebras over the comonad $\pi_{!}\circ \pi^*$. It is clear that the underlying spectrum of this comonad applied to $\mathbb{S}$ is $\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{Z}]$, and one can trace through multiplicative structures to see that this is an equivalence of $E_\infty$-rings, giving the desired identification of categories.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To identify this further with $QCoh(B\mathbb{G}_m)$ we present the latter as the totalization of the cosimplicial diagram of module categories
$$
Sp \rightrightarrows Mod(\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{Z}]) \text{(three arrows)} Mod(\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{Z}])\otimes_{Sp} Mod(\mathbb{S}[\mathbb{Z}]) ...
$$
which may be augmented by the addition of $\pi_!:Sp^{gr}\to Sp$ on the left. The comonadicity of $\pi_!$ can then be used to identify $Sp^{gr}$ with the totalization of the above diagram, giving the desired result.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prove the main result, we again use the theory of monads. The categories $QCoh(\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m)$ and $Sp^{fil}$ are monadic over $QCoh(B\mathbb{G}_m)$ and $Sp^{gr}$ respectively. The latter is simple to describe, we take modules over the graded ring object $\mathbb{S}[\tau]$ which has underlying graded spectrum $\mathbb{S}$ in nonnegative degrees to encode the action of $\tau$ and hence the structure maps of a filtered object. For the categories of quasicoherent sheaves, we take modules over the pushforward $\theta_*\mathcal{O}_{\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m}$ of the unit along the map $\theta: \mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m \to B\mathbb{G}_m$, which is the image of $\mathbb{A}^1\to Spec\mathbb{S}$ under $\mathbb{G}_m$ homotopy orbits. Having identified the two base categories, the proof is finished by showing that under our furnished equivalence we have $\theta_*\mathcal{O}_{\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m}\mapsto \mathbb{S}[\tau]$. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we prodive another geometric interpretation of the special&#x2F;generic fiber philosophy. The associated graded functor may now be viewed as a functor $gr: QCoh(\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m) \to QCoh(B\mathbb{G}_m)$ which we would like to describe without reference to the above equivalence. Similarly, the realization functor may be viewed as a functor $QCoh(\mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m) \to QCoh(Spec\mathbb{S})\simeq Sp$. Moulinos shows that this latter functor is exactly the pullback of the unique map of spectral stacks $Spec\mathbb{S} \to \mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m$ and the former is the pullback of the unique map of spectral stacks $B\mathbb{G}_m\to \mathbb{A}^1&#x2F;\mathbb{G}_m$.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Red-Shift for the Greek Alphabet</title>
        <published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://maxj.phd/posts/greek/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://maxj.phd/posts/greek/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction-and-references&quot;&gt;Introduction and References&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I hope to provide a helpful expository on the celebrated &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.jstor.org&#x2F;stable&#x2F;1971440&quot;&gt;Nilpotence 1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; paper of Devinatz, Hopkins, and Smith.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Motivic Filtrations on TP&#x2F;TC (WIP)</title>
        <published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://maxj.phd/posts/motfil/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://maxj.phd/posts/motfil/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction-and-references&quot;&gt;Introduction and References&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to write about a pair of papers, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1802.03261&quot;&gt;BMS2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2206.11208&quot;&gt;HRW&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in order to explain the construction of certain filtrations on Topological Cyclic homology for quasisyntomic discrete rings (the BMS paper) and chromatically quasisyntomic commutative ring spectra (the HRW paper).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this note is to expand upon some of the constructions in both papers and hopefully provide a useful exposition in the process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;preliminaries-for-the-discrete-case&quot;&gt;Preliminaries for the Discrete Case&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reminders-on-thh-tc-and-tp&quot;&gt;Reminders on THH, TC, and TP&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;homotopy-fixed-point-and-tate-spectral-sequences&quot;&gt;Homotopy Fixed Point and Tate Spectral Sequences&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sites-qrsp-and-qsyn&quot;&gt;The sites QRSP and QSyn&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;preliminaries-for-the-ring-spectrum-case&quot;&gt;Preliminaries for the Ring Spectrum Case&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;chromatically-quasisyntomic-rings&quot;&gt;Chromatically Quasisyntomic Rings&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-filtered-model-for-stable-motivic-homotopy&quot;&gt;A Filtered Model for Stable Motivic Homotopy&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Expository on Nilpotence 1 (WIP)</title>
        <published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://maxj.phd/posts/nilp1/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://maxj.phd/posts/nilp1/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction-and-references&quot;&gt;Introduction and References&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to write about a pair of papers, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;1802.03261&quot;&gt;BMS2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2206.11208&quot;&gt;HRW&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in order to explain the construction of certain filtrations on Topological Cyclic homology for quasisyntomic discrete rings (the BMS paper) and chromatically quasisyntomic commutative ring spectra (the HRW paper).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this note is to expand upon some of the constructions in both papers and hopefully provide a useful exposition in the process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;preliminaries-for-the-discrete-case&quot;&gt;Preliminaries for the Discrete Case&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reminders-on-thh-tc-and-tp&quot;&gt;Reminders on THH, TC, and TP&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;homotopy-fixed-point-and-tate-spectral-sequences&quot;&gt;Homotopy Fixed Point and Tate Spectral Sequences&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sites-qrsp-and-qsyn&quot;&gt;The sites QRSP and QSyn&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;preliminaries-for-the-ring-spectrum-case&quot;&gt;Preliminaries for the Ring Spectrum Case&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;chromatically-quasisyntomic-rings&quot;&gt;Chromatically Quasisyntomic Rings&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-filtered-model-for-stable-motivic-homotopy&quot;&gt;A Filtered Model for Stable Motivic Homotopy&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
